<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Rustlog</title><link href="https://lifthrasiir.github.io/rustlog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://lifthrasiir.github.io/rustlog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://lifthrasiir.github.io/rustlog/</id><updated>2014-12-06T18:48:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>The Beginning</title><link href="https://lifthrasiir.github.io/rustlog/the-beginning.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-06T18:48:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kang Seonghoon</name></author><id>tag:lifthrasiir.github.io,2014-12-06:rustlog/the-beginning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to the first post to the Rustlog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For everyone &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; interested about the author:
I'm &lt;a href="http://mearie.org/about/kang-seonghoon.en"&gt;Kang Seonghoon&lt;/a&gt;, a Korean software developer doing funky things.
In the world of Rust I'm probably best known for
&lt;a href="https://github.com/lifthrasiir/rust-encoding"&gt;rust-encoding&lt;/a&gt;, a comprehensive character encoding library.
I also happen to enjoy talking on Moznet #rust (as known as &lt;code&gt;Yurume&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what the hell is this blog?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a separate personal &lt;a href="http://j.mearie.org/"&gt;journal&lt;/a&gt; in my website.
Probably many of you wouldn't understand its contents;
it's almost Korean only, and even though I've done some works to
make the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; website bilingual,
the journal remains quite exclusive in Korean.
(I do have some &lt;a href="http://j.mearie.org/tagged/english"&gt;English posts&lt;/a&gt; though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I have a desire to write useful posts in English.
That's why I sometimes write to &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/lifthrasiir/"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;.
It is technically not a blog, but at least it is a comfortable place
to write a Markdown post.
I also have been motivated by the concept of "worklog"
as a daily diary for logging the day's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm going to give a shot.
&lt;strong&gt;Every Rust-related post in English from now on will go here.
Also, I'll try to write a short remainder about
whatever I've done with Rust every day ("worklog").&lt;/strong&gt;
I know this is very hard from the experience,
but at least I'll try to do so.
I'm kind of a yak-shaving personnel,
but this time I chose to stick to &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;
as it seems easy to install and &lt;em&gt;forget&lt;/em&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd appreciate any feedback on the post available here,
but unless there is a link to the explicit feedback form,
please direct any feedback to my &lt;a href="http://mearie.org/about/contact.en"&gt;personal email&lt;/a&gt;.
I'm close to &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; the direct comments, so sorry about that.
And obviously my writing solely represents my own opinion
and not my employer's or organization's. :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>